This afternoon at 5:00
Il Duce will speak
to the nation!
You are ordered
to turn your radios on!
All of you who have radio sets
and radio gramophones
are ordered to turn them on.
Mussolini will speak
to all Italians!
You are authorised by order
of the Fascist government
to interrupt your work.
This afternoon at 5:00
Il Duce will speak
to the nation.
I was twelve and a half
when I saw her for the first time.
Even though I'm older now
and my mind plays tricks on me,
I remember it well.
Τhat day, Mussolini declared war
on France and Great Britain
and I got my first bicycle.
The frame is British,
the gears are French,
and the brakes are from...
I forget.
But the chain is Sicilian...
always keep it greasy.
- Are you sure it's safe?
- I have new bikes too.
Mimi, we're at war.
Who can afford a new bicycle?
Fighting men...
on land, on sea
and in the air,
Blackshirts of the revolution,
men and women of Italy
and the Kingdom of Albania
hear this...
Except for my father, who wasn't
very fond of "Our Great Leader"
everyone in town was happy
that Italy was going to war.
Maybe they couldn't see,
and I surely couldn't have known
how that day would
mark my life forever.
The hour...
of decisions from which
there is no return.
Pino, think this ant knows
he's dead meat?
Who knows?
If he's like you,
he doesn't know shit.
The declaration of war
has already been delivered
to the ambassadors.
I'm free from misery.
Mary's son is my Lord.
Hey, guys!
Lucky bastard,
he's got a new bicycle!
Man, she's beautiful!
It's almost brand new.
Custom-made,
just like the racers.
- Now you're a man, like us.
- So I can join the gang?
- "Don Agostino"?
- Okay by me.
- "Don Nicola"?
- I'd let him in.
- "Don Tonino"?
- Sure.
And you, "Don Sasa"?
I don't want some kid
poking into our business.
- Why? What are you doing?
- Can you keep your mouth shut?
She's coming!
What's going on?
If you wanna be one of us,
just shut up and watch.
Who is she?
The deaf guy's daughter,
our new Latin teacher.
- What's her name?
- What a wonderful ass!
What I wouldn't give
for an hour with her!
- Too bad she's married.
- If she weren't...
What's her name?
Malena, the most beautiful ass
in Castelcuto.
The sun is bigger
than the moon.
Sol maior est quam lunam.
Or sol maior est luna.
Can I screw your daughter,
you deaf old fart?
Yes, but hurry.
I love honesty
more than wealth.
Seven thumbs long!
- Seven and a half thumbs!
- Mine's a bazooka!
- I got eight!
- Eight is nothing!
That's just tickling a woman!
One, two... three and two is five,
two is seven and two is nine.
Torpedo!
My submarine
will rip Malena in half!
Once I skipped school
and went by Malena's house.
She was at the window,
and she called out to me.
I thought she wanted me
to get her some cigarettes.
I went up for the money,
and her robe fell open.
And there she was,
naked as the day
she was born.
Holy shit!
She did it on purpose
to excite me.
I was an idiot.
I should have jumped at the chance.
If it happens again,
I'll bang her brains out.
She'd quit smoking first.
She knows you've got no balls.
You little runt,
you've been here for two hours
and you still haven't
measured yourself.
Measure it!
One, two...
three, four...
five...
Only six!
You know what they say
about a kid in short pants?
Short pants: short dick!
Fuck off. My thumbs are twice
as big as yours!
Bullshit!
Who's got the biggest dick
now, runt?
You do!
No, I am Il Duce!
Nobody's bigger than me!
- Ooh. Renato's skipping school.
- Shh!
You, come here!
I need some cigarettes.
What cigarettes do you want?
Macedonia Extra.
I remember this suit very well.
It's your father's.
I sewed it 20 years ago,
and it still looks brand new.
He only wore it to his wedding.
He wants to keep it for his funeral.
If he's buried in this suit,
he'll go straight to heaven!
- My father's still young.
- And you're too young for long pants.
I didn't ask
for your opinion, sir.
- Does he know about this?
- Of course he does!
You little scoundrel,
what the hell is this?
Come here, mister.
So you want to skip school?
Fine. Who didn't at your age?
Leave him alone!
I know what I'm doing.
And you let your friends
beat you up.
Fair enough.
Even though when I was your age,
I'd beat my friends up!
But stealing trousers
from your father
and getting them altered
for yourself
is just plain wrong!
But, Papa,
you don't understand!
Understand?
Who said you could speak?
I'm ashamed
to wear short pants!
What about knickers?
They're almost long pants!
Enough! He's still a child!
I'll tell our party secretary you won't
let me go to the Fascist exercises.
Let's make a deal:
The day someone cracks the skull
of "Our Great Leader"...
then you'll get long pants.
Swear it.
A beautiful young woman
all alone here. It's a crime.
- Who's he talking about?
- Malena Scordia, Nino's sexy new wife.
She must have somebody on the side,
it's inevitable!
- Number fifteen!
- Me.
Right. Nino brings her from her village
with her ailing father.
And then a month later, boom...
Nino's called to the war.
Who here wants to bet
she's sleeping all alone?
Not me!
Why don't you let me
sit with the others?
You're too young
to sit in the adult chair.
- Good night, comrade.
- Hey, who's out after curfew?
Ah, it's you, Roberto.
And on the home front,
report of fuel and food shortages
are beginning to mount.
In the islands
and outlying areas
rationing of flour and sugar
will continue...
But, son, if you don't know the title,
how can I help you?
It's that pretty, romantic one...
"Ma L'Amore No".
Why didn't you say so?
Ten lire.
Pay at the cashier's.
- Don't you test it?
- What for?
- It might be defective.
- It's brand new!
Miss Malena,
this heart of mine, on fire,
has written so many letters
and if I didn't have the courage
to send them to you
it was only because I didn't want
to do you harm.
So forgive me if I dare
to send you this one.
I want you to know
that this town has many gossips,
who say bad things about you...
that you have a secret lover.
I know it's not true.
You don't have anyone.
After your husband,
the only man in your life is me.
I have to go. I'll see you
at school tomorrow.
So long!
Don't get lost!
Malena's up
in the employment office.
- Looking for a job again?
- But who will ever hire her?
No one in this town.
I've got a job for her...
Little boy, let me get by.
Hey, baby,
give a soldier a break!
Mr Lawyer!
Your newspaper's upside down!
Mind your own fucking business!
Good morning, Signora Malena,
are you well?
How is your father?
May I?
The show's over!
She's gone now!
I forgot the key!
So it's true what people say!
What's the matter with you?
You look so strange.
You've poisoned me
with your lies.
What lies?
I've never spoken to you.
I knew it from the start...
you're a loose woman.
But I've never
done anything wrong.
Liar! I've been following you
on my bicycle!
I know where you went.
I know everything!
- Τhe lawyer, the dentist!
- No, Renato, I love only you!
Liar!
- Amoroso.
- Here!
- Cali.
- Costanza.
- Here!
Professor, can I put my dick
between Malena's tits?
Can I put mine in her mouth?
Can I put mine
between her legs?
Okay, but one at a time!
You're all sons of bitches!
Why didn't she marry someone
from her own village?
I'm sure no one wanted her.
- They say she's a seamstress.
- But she's so vulgar.
My son says she looks fake.
My husband says he wouldn't touch her
with a ten-foot pole.
The Baron Bonta's mistress
is much nicer.
At least Gina does everything
in the open.
The baron screws her once a week
and then goes back to Palermo.
Malena acts so superior.
Like we don't know what she's up to.
Wait and see.
She'll get hers.
The headquarters
of the armed forces communicates:
"Our brave and invincible fighting men
have delivered a powerful blow
"to the faceless war machine
unleashed by the Allies.
"In order to ensure
the continued strength and vitality,
"of our forces at the front,
"all payment of civic pensions
"will again be postponed..."
It's ready.
Thank you.
It's not much,
but it's all we can afford.
Me Tarzan, you Malena.
Renato, you've got the biggest gun
in the West!
You're going to go blind!
Right rank!
Eyes front! Arms out, arms high,
in quick succession!
Have you heard?
Malena's husband was killed.
My father told me.
He read the telegram.
Malena is available!
Comrades of Castelcuto,
we are gathered here today
to share in the tragic
but honourable mourning
which has struck our town.
To express our deepest condolences
for the loss
of Lt Nino Scordia,
heroically killed in action
in Northern Africa...
...and to his bride Maddalena
who, stricken with grief,
unfortunately isn't here with us.
- She's already out looking!
- She'll need a warm bed now!
But she is with us in spirit
because Sicilian women,
with their hardships,
with their sacrifices,
march shoulder to shoulder
with fighting men.
The martyrdom of our fellow citizen
in defence of his country
was not a useless sacrifice.
- Lt Cadei is so handsome.
- A lucky girl will catch him!
...that will carry us to the
final victory of the Fascist Empire!
Long live Il Duce!
From now on
I'll be at your side.
Forever. I promise.
Just give me time to grow up.
Now she'll take a lover
for sure!
"Once in the sack,
there's no looking back!"
She knows that.
She's 27 years old.
She knows her way
around the block!
Cusimano, the dentist,
has gone crazy for her.
One day he was distracted
as she walked by
and pulled a healthy tooth
instead of the rotten one!
Dentist or not,
why haven't we seen her lately?
Guess she's too busy!
They say she's fooling around
with a shopkeeper in Catania
with subversive tendencies.
Some say Cusimano,
the dentist.
- A family man. It's disgraceful!
- When you're a born whore...
I hear the priest
has received anonymous letters
saying her lover
is this man, that man.
The voice of the people
is the voice of God!
I can't talk to anyone
about my personal problems.
They're too intimate.
But you seem nice.
I'd like to confide in you.
Every day,
I'll light a candle for you.
I'll even come to Mass
on Sunday.
But you must protect Malena Scordia
from the town.
Yes, the widow... at least for a few years.
Then I'll take over.
I am always at your service.
Renewed condolences, Malena.
What a piece of ass!
Son of a bitch!
You little runt!
Come back here!
- Can't you sing in Italian?
- Can't you speak German?
Renato, get up. It's late.
Monster!
You're a fetishist,
a sadomasochist,
or even worse, a pervert!
- What is that?
- It's just a French hat, Ma!
Shame on you!
- How pretty. Can I keep them?
- You shameless girl!
What are you looking at?
Get out of here!
Come here, you little pig!
- Goddam pervert!
- What did I do?
You're not permitted to sit
at the table with us, understand?
- Answer me!
- Okay!
You no longer have the right
to speak to your sisters, understand?
Lock me up! I'll show you!
You're not to leave this room
until further notice!
Son, at least have some soup.
It will do you good.
Pietro, he hasn't eaten
for three days.
In the Soviet Union,
they never eat. Still...
What is this shit?
The Fascists gave it to us.
At least it looks like coffee.
Sure, and I look
like Vittorio De Sica.
Everything they give us
is terrible!
Look at these pockets.
They're always ripping open!
This cheap thread
doesn't hold the stitches!
The thread isn't the problem!
While our son recites poetry,
his hands go to work in his pockets!
What does that mean?
Do you get it now?
Just as well! Don't fix them.
Sew the pockets closed!
But he'll have no pockets?
He'll work it out.
It will be good for his health!
Lights out!
"...that the weary spirit may ne'er
repose in more restful harbour..."
- Has he gone crazy?
- I think he's gone blind.
"While upon women's work
you sat intent
"content with the vague future
you held in mind
"was the scented May,
and thus you used to spend your days."
- This child needs air.
- Air?
Air.
Good morning, Professor.
This letter is for you.
It says "urgent".
You're dishonoured.
Your daughter Malena is sleeping
with the whole town.
It was an anonymous letter,
but I read it!
It says Malena is a whore
with everyone in town!
So there's hope for us too!
Take it back!
I'll bust your ass,
Mr Short Pants!
Tonight was wonderful.
For me too.
I know it's
been only ten months since.
But maybe I can see you again.
All right. You win. Tomorrow.
Okay, as long as
I'm not on duty.
- Thanks for the flowers.
- You're welcome.
Take care of yourself.
So see you tomorrow?
- Until then.
- Good night, Leone.
What time?
- Good evening, sir.
- Good evening, my ass!
How dare you
pester my fiancee!
There must be a misunderstanding.
I was invited.
You're a liar and a bastard!
Because I'm in uniform,
I cannot retaliate, sir.
- But you will answer to me.
- Anytime. Anywhere.
Coward, scoundrel!
Get up.
Come here! I'll tear you apart,
you coward!
I'll break you in two!
Let me go! Or I'll have
to get tough with you!
Here's the adulterer!
My wife!
- Officer, look! He's cheating on me!
- With a man?
With a traitor!
You said you wouldn't touch her
with a ten-foot pole!
It's the dentist!
I've been spying on you
a long time, you bastard!
And as for you
go steal husbands
from your own village, you whore!
We knew she had one lover,
but two?
But where does the dentist fit in?
He fits in between her legs!
Her father was forced
to quit the school in disgrace.
He never wants
to see his daughter Malena again.
And the dentist's wife
kicked him out of his house.
That dragon of a wife
will drag him into court!
What's the dentist got to do
with it, poor guy?
Malena's the whore!
She should be taken to court!
That Lt Cadei
seemed like such a gentleman.
How could he get mixed up
in this?
Everyone knows
she's a home wrecker.
The lieutenant was asking for it!
She's not from here.
She forgets where she is.
Will they go to court?
Of course, she could go to jail.
He's a married man!
The dentist needed three stitches
in his head.
But the dentist
swore at the soldier first.
That's insulting an officer.
We'll all end up in court!
While we were
watching her caboose
the lieutenant and the dentist
were riding the train!
She's either going
to the lawyer's or the notary's.
Sure, but what will she do
with two old men like them?
- Excuse me.
- Come in.
Can I help you?
May I speak
to Lawyer Centorbi?
Please have a seat.
Sir, it's the widow Scordia!
Can it be true?
Beautiful Madonna!
Have her come in.
Please sit down.
Charmed.
We now continue with the testimony
of Maddalena Bonsignore,
the widow Scordia,
called Malena.
She could get two years in prison.
Everything will be fine, trust me.
You're accused of involving
Dr Gaspare Cusimano
in a secret
and amorous relationship
aimed at the breaking up
of his family.
Do you know Dr Cusimano?
Yes.
Are you or have you ever been
his fiancee?
Absolutely not.
How could I be engaged
to a married man?
Why was Cusimano,
at that unusual hour
on his way to your house?
I don't know.
Had he been in your company
on previous evenings?
Yes, once.
Where?
At my house.
Jumped right in, the dentist did.
He looks stupid, but...
How long did he stay?
Not long.
What did you do?
He brought me some medicine
for my father.
If it was for your father,
why did he bring it to you?
I don't know.
What did you do after
he gave you the medicine?
He said goodbye and left.
Then why
has Cusimano,
a reputable professional,
who, five years ago,
had the honour of extracting
one of Il Duce's teeth
publicly declare
that he is your fiance?
He made that up.
I had nothing to do with it.
Your husband's crazy.
What kind of relationship
did you have with Lt Cadei?
I'm a widow.
My business
and that of Lt Cadei
are no concern of the law.
All right.
Did you know that,
as a result of these affairs
Lt Cadei was transferred
to Albania?
One down.
And before his departure,
he was questioned in judicial inquiry.
Clerk.
He declared to have encountered
the widow Scordia only twice
in her home
and to have had
no amorous relationship
considering their relationship
"just a casual friendship."
Son of a bitch.
Lt Cadei was received
by my client
and she makes no secret
about having had for him
certain feelings.
But unlike the married Cusimano
who was, let's face it, guilty
of a pre-senile dimming
of the senses
of an intoxicating
kaleidoscope of desires...
What's he saying?
Unlike the family man Cusimano,
Cadei is...
...and was
a bachelor!
Clever, that lawyer.
He's a bachelor himself.
Careful investigation
of the facts tell us, therefore
that the Scordia woman
committed no other crime
than that of being ill-fated,
alone
and beautiful.
Here is her crime:
her beauty!
And from here, the envy,
the lies,
the disgrace
that have deprived her
even of a father's trust!
And yet, she herself
is still in silent agony,
in faraway East Africa.
In the beating heart
of our argument
is an audacious,
but nonetheless valid, thesis,
which asks just one question:
Can a young woman
after the odyssey of a widowhood
endured for the love of country
hope for protection
in the shelter of a new life?
Does she have the right
to yearn for, and to write
a new ending
to her own love story?
Your Honour,
the citizens of Castelcuto reply:
"Yes!"
Will Cusimano leave me alone now?
Of course.
He's been put into
a psychiatric clinic.
He wants to volunteer
for the Forces in East Africa.
He doesn't realise
we lost Africa ages ago!
But let's forget Cusimano
and the fickle Lieutenant Cadei.
Let's get to us!
I know it's not much.
But it's all I have.
They've cut my pension.
Don't you understand?
That's peanuts!
My fee is much more than that.
You'll never have enough money!
But how will I ever repay you?
It's very easy, my sweet.
- What are you saying?
- Be with me, my love!
I'm in love with you!
A woman shouldn't be alone
during these hard times.
I am a wealthy man.
You won't find better.
I'll take care of your father.
You'll never have to worry again.
I forgive her.
She did it
to pay her lawyer's fee
only once and never again.
But you didn't keep our agreement.
Now we're even.
...in the South, the Allied bombings
have forced thousands to flee.
Refugees are pouring into
the countryside and the port towns.
Citizens of these regions
have been alerted
to possible severe food shortages
and outbreaks of disease.
Signora Malena,
a more capable person than me
wrote that the only true love
is unrequited love.
Now I understand why.
It's been so long since you
last came out of your house.
But the longer we are apart,
the stronger my love becomes.
Τhey say you're about to marry
Centorbi, the lawyer.
I know how badly
they treat you here
how the women in the market
won't sell you any good food
and no man would hire you
for fear of his wife.
But how will you manage to live
with a fat, old man,
so ugly that no girl
ever wanted him?
Τhey say he never washes
and stinks like a goat.
How will your smooth, white skin,
bear rubbing against
the sweat of an old man,
who never does anything
without his mother's consent?
Is it true you're getting married?
What are you writing?
Give me that! Let me see!
Get out!
Stand up straight.
A little longer, Don Placido.
More room in the waist,
for when he gets bigger.
Will they be ready tomorrow?
The war has ruined my business,
but it still takes time.
...as Allied bombings continue.
Wait for me.
Lord, help me with my mother,
I beg you.
Moron!
Idiot!
You can't treat me like a child.
I'm a grown man!
Get this straight!
Your father's good name will never
belong to that disgusting whore!
Never! Never!
The lawyer was left high and dry!
His mother still bathes him
every Saturday!
Malena always has someone
throwing a wrench in the works!
It won't be hard finding someone
to replace the lawyer!
Come on, sit down.
The next in line
already has a plan.
Yeah, his plan is in his pants.
- A cut and shave.
- Right away, sir.
Good morning, Antonio.
I brought some sugar and flour.
- What about the bread?
- The best.
- I can't pay right now.
- That's no problem.
I'm sure we can find a way
to make you some money.
Hurry, there's someone else
over here!
Stand back!
It's Professor Bonsignore.
Malena's father.
I'm here for you.
Condolences, Signora Scordia.
Condolences.
Step aside, kid.
Signora, what can we do?
We're in the Lord's hands.
Don't forget my offer.
You don't have to go hungry.
Attention, loyal citizens!
This is "a call to arms".
We must maintain our faith
and hope in the Republic
in the face
of imperialistic aggression!
Despite recent setbacks
on the front
and escalating hardships at home
remember that nothing can dim
our fervour
for our glorious homeland!
Can you believe it?
Just a few years ago,
Il Duce promised
that the Nazis
would never occupy Sicily.
Now he's sold us down the river!
Look!
The Germans are everywhere!
- Look who's here.
- She's a redhead now.
Look how she's put together.
I'd like to cut off that hair.
I'd skin her alive!
How disgusting!
- Who is it?
- It's me.
- Me who?
- Salvatore. Antonio sent me.
I brought you some more food.
Come in.
- Your hair looks terrific.
- Do you like it?
- Yes, it makes you look younger.
- Thank you.
I can come every Thursday!
As long as you bring the food.
Now she's even screwing
the Germans.
- Who's that?
- Malena Scordia, the slut.
She's teamed up
with that other whore, Gina.
But with the Germans?
Seems there are gymnastics
at the Moderno Hotel.
The two whores run
from room to room
servicing a dozen officers
at a time.
Holy shit!
My good woman, this child
is possessed by the devil!
Jesus, Mary and Joseph!
That's enough!
It looks like you're posing for
Michelangelo's Pieta of the poor!
Evil eye on blood is fed.
Hold on fast till death is past.
Exorcise the devil from this child.
Goat red, on wood fed,
hold on fast.
Head and tail,
evil eye release this child.
Cast the devil into the wild.
Shameful! Disgraceful!
They cured my uncle this way
and he had cholera!
Your son's not sick!
He's becoming a man!
With a dick this big,
he needs to fuck!
Renato, wait here for me.
Come here. Come on.
Close the door.
- My father?
- He's coming.
Ladies!
Choose the one you like.
What do we have here?
Fresh young meat.
Lupetta, up to the room.
Treat him right.
- What's your name?
- Amoroso Renato.
What a romantic name!
Tonight we either die in a bombing
or end up in jail.
Go ahead.
- Is it your first time?
- No.
I've imagined it many times.
Let's go give that shameless whore
what she deserves.
Stay back.
This is between the women.
Now you'll see what happens
when you steal our men
and sleep with the filthy Germans.
It's the end
of spreading your legs, whore!
Now let's see
what men make of you!
This will teach you some respect!
The wicked come to a wicked end.
The madame is served.
Get lost!
Disappear!
I know that face.
Who is it?
Nino Scordia, Malena's husband.
Malena, the one who did it
with the Germans.
Poor guy.
He was better off dead.
Isn't that Malena's husband?
Hey, Giovanni,
there's a strange guy.
Do you know Malena Scordia?
Who's she?
Who are you?
This is my family's house!
We don't know anything.
When we came,
no one was living here.
No one?
Poor guy.
No one will tell him the truth.
What would you say,
"I hear your wife is a prostitute"?
I hear she's still
a great piece of ass.
I lost an arm. I wasn't dead!
Then I was taken prisoner in India
and I contracted malaria.
Tell him.
Me "boy-bar."
I have to get the coffee cups.
My family has lived in this town
for generations.
Now no one will talk to me.
My house is a refugee camp,
and my wife has disappeared.
No one in town knows where she is.
Help me find her.
I want to bring her home.
Excuse me. Don't you remember me?
I'm Nino Scordia.
You mistake me for someone else.
Could I have a light?
You were the Fascist secretary,
and you were his deputy.
You can help me.
Do you know what happened
to my wife?
Didn't she join
the Communist Party?
She was photographed
with her arms
around the Commie leader.
You're a family of heroes!
You're right.
Those who fought the war
for you bastards aren't heroes.
Go take a walk through
the brothels of Sicily.
You may find your wife there!
Wait a minute. Come back!
Dear Signor Scordia,
forgive me if I don't have the courage
to speak man to man.
These last months have
taught me much about courage,
even if I have found little myself.
I'm the only one who knows
the truth about your wife.
Around here, they only say
bad things about her.
But believe me,
your wife Malena
was faithful to you.
You are the only man she loved.
This is the honest truth.
It is true,
a lot of things happened,
but back then,
you had been dead a long time.
Τhe last time I saw her,
she was on a train for Messina.
Best of luck.
I should sign "a friend",
like all anonymous letters,
but my name is Renato.
Good morning, Judge.
All is well, thank God.
Eat up, my sweet pea.
Sons of bitches!
Look who's here!
Giorgio, look who's here!
Why are you all looking
at that woman?
It's nothing.
I saw them in the square.
They were walking arm in arm.
Quiet. She's here!
It took a lot of courage
to come back.
Look who's here.
I heard it,
but I didn't believe it.
What have they got to look at?
They should leave her in peace.
She's got some wrinkles
around her eyes.
She's put on weight too.
But she's still beautiful.
Good morning, Mrs Scordia.
Good morning.
Want some nice tomatoes?
They cost less over there.
Thank you.
Nice things here!
Like it, Signora Malena?
- Try it on.
- No, that's okay.
- It's no problem.
- Another time.
Give me your bag.
We'll discuss it later.
Good morning, Signora Malena.
It's okay. I'll get it.
Thank you.
Thank you for your help.
Good luck, Signora Malena.
I pedalled as fast as I could,
as if I were escaping
from longing, from innocence,
from her.
Time has passed,
and I have loved many women.
And as they've held me close,
and asked if I will remember them
I've said,
"Yes, I will remember you."
But the only one
I've never forgotten
is the one who never asked...
Malena.