(IN FRENCH)
Thank you, captain.
Well?
The target is still in the same place.
Target is leaving the apartment.
Ten seconds.
Start the engine.
(SPEAKS FRENCH)
(♪♪♪)
Underwear or no underwear today?
Be a little more professional, guys.
(♪♪♪)
She's turning left.
She's going to her usual cafe.
(IN FRENCH) Hello.
Hello.
May I take your order?
A tea with milk, an orange juice and...
And a croissant.
It's already ordered.
Thank you.
Do you have a visual?
We have a visual.
She's drinking her tea.
COURSON: (ON RADIO)
Come again?
She's drinking her tea!
Did you ask for a tea, sir?
No, no. Thank you.
(♪♪♪)
- COURIER: Hello, sir.
- WAITER: Hello.
I'm looking for Ms. Elise Ward.
That's Ms. Ward over there.
Okay. Thank, you.
Hello. Elise Ward?
- Yes, it's me.
- I have an envelope for you.
Somebody is talking to her.
Looks like a courier.
(PHONE RINGING)
- (IN ENGLISH) Yes?
- COURSON: She's at her usual cafe.
She's speaking with a man.
Looks like a messenger, you said to
call if anything changed in her routine.
Stay on his face. His face.
Do you think it's Alexander Pearce?
I think everybody is Pearce.
No, no. It's okay. It's a gift.
Thank you.
Oh, voila.
- Goodbye.
(♪♪♪)
All right, grab him.
(IN FRENCH) Take him.
Let's get him.
Sir.
Sir, stop! Police!
COURIER:
What's going on?
You are under arrest.
Financial Crimes Division.
- Division what?
- Shh!
COURIER:
Guys, I'm working!
ELISE: (IN ENGLISH WITH BRITISH ACCENT)
Elise, you have no reason to trust me anymore,
but give me a chance to explain myself.
I know the police are watching you.
We have to throw them off the trail.
Board the 8:22 at the Gare de Lyon,
pick someone my height and build
and make them believe it is me.
(♪♪♪)
Burn this letter.
It is important you follow
my instructions precisely.
I love you. Alexander.
It's from him.
Save that letter. Go in now.
Save that letter.
(IN FRENCH)
Daniel, get over there now.
(DANIEL SHOUTING IN FRENCH)
Well?
(IN ENGLISH)
The letter is burnt to shit.
Don't fucking touch it.
Take the ashes, take them to the van.
I'll send you someone.
(♪♪♪)
(IN FRENCH)
Drive around to the other side! Go!
Turn right at the end.
Faster!
(♪♪♪)
(COURSON SHOUTING IN FRENCH)
(COURSON SPEAKS FRENCH)
(CHATTERING)
(SPEAKS FRENCH)
ASSISTANT:
Wednesday meeting.
Specialist pool.
So Alexander Pearce has a new face,
just as you suspected.
I'd have thought it must've taken
quite a lot of the money
he stole from Reginald Shaw
to finance this transformation.
Ach med Tchebali.
Bicycle courier of Algerian descent.
Not only has Pearce acquired a wife
and child,
he's also 4 inches shorter
than he used to be.
That must have been a big item
of expenditure.
Congratulations, Acheson.
You have, indeed, cracked this case.
Letter to Inspector Collins.
Sir, this morning, she received a note,
we have strong reason to believe...
Alexander Pearce has 744 million
in illegal assets
that, given he is a British subject,
we might seize.
Fraud complaints.
This operation, so far,
has cost me 8 million.
If I thought there were more
than a one-in-a-hundred chance
you could be successful,
it would be rational for me
to continue this operation.
Money laundering.
I do not.
- Yes, that's an amendment.
- Yes.
There.
It needs redrafting.
Yes, sir.
- Everything after code seven.
- Thank you, sir.
There's just one more.
Home Office.
Yes, and that's it.
Yes. That's it.
(♪♪♪)
(BLEEPING)
"Eight twenty-two."
- Projection for the pension plan fraud.
- Not now.
"Eight twenty-two. Lyon."
Are they meeting in Lyon at 8:22?
Gare de Lyon, perhaps?
Gare de Lyon.
(BLEEPING)
That's it. Gare de Lyon.
The train station.
She's getting on an 8:22 train. Go.
(♪♪♪)
ELISE:
"Board the 8:22 at the Gare de Lyon."
ELISE: "Pick someone my height and
build, make them believe it is me."
(♪♪♪)
- I'm sorry.
- What for?
Mind me smoking?
It's not a real cigarette.
- What?
- It's electronic.
Delivers the same amount of nicotine,
but the smoke is water vapor.
Yeah. Watch.
LED light.
That's somewhat disappointing.
Would you have me smoking for real?
I would rather you be a man
who did exactly as he pleased.
- I'm Elise.
- I'm Frank.
That's a terrible name.
Heh, heh.
It's the only one I've got.
- Maybe we can find you another.
- Okay.
- You're British.
- Hm.
- I'm American.
Hm.
What brings you to Venice?
You read spy novels.
I'm a mysterious woman on a train.
You tell me what my story is.
Okay. Um...
I think you'd be a diplomatic attache.
Hm.
Or maybe a girl from East Germany
whose father's been kidnapped
and they're blackmailing you
into stealing something for them.
Probably a microfilm.
There's usually microfilm involved.
- What awaits me?
- Trouble, certainly.
- Danger?
- Oh, yeah.
You'll be shot at
in less than two chapters.
Hm.
Is there a man in my life?
(CHUCKLES)
Have to wait and see.
- I nvite me to dinner, Frank.
- What?
Would you like to have dinner?
Women don't like questions.
- Join me for dinner.
- Too demanding.
Join me for dinner?
Another question.
I'm having dinner,
if you'd care to join me.
(♪♪♪)
Musician.
Bartender.
(SIGHS)
I give up.
Math. I teach math.
I would not have guessed that.
I'd imagine
you're the cool math teacher.
Still a math teacher.
DANIEL: (IN FRENCH)
How about a photo?
Go right ahead.
Make me look good.
(CAMERA CLICKS)
(BLEEP)
(♪♪♪)
Could this be Pearce?
We still working on that?
Well, I only have the sketches
to go by, so...
Ectomorph, yes.
Same basic phenotype.
Bottom line, could be him.
I knew he couldn't leave her.
Run a worldwide blind check on that face.
I bet you 10 quid there's no match.
Okay, what case number
do you want to book it under?
- Just run it.
- Do you really think it's Pearce?
Run it.
Get me Italian Interpol.
(BLEEPING)
(BOTH WHISPERING INDISTINCTLY)
I have a strange feeling
that those two people over there
are watching us.
Do you know something?
I think you're right.
Really?
(LAUGHING)
You're the paranoid math teacher.
(♪♪♪)
(MAN SPEAKING ITALIAN ON PA)
(IN ITALIAN)
Memorize his face.
The train arrives in ten minutes.
As soon as he steps off, arrest him.
(♪♪♪)
So, what are you doing all alone
in the city of lovers?
Is there no one in your life?
There was.
What happened?
She left me.
I'm sorry to hear that, Frank.
(WOMAN SPEAKING ITALIAN ON PA)
WOMAN: (IN ENGLISH ON PA) Arrival at train
station Venezia Santa Lucia in 10 minutes.
End of the line.
Guess I should go
get my suitcase and stuff.
Goodbye.
Thank you.
(BLEEPING)
Oh, shit.
- Sir, I...
- Wait.
"Pick someone my height and build
and make them believe it's me."
We did get an exact match.
He's a math teacher from Madison
Community College. Frank Tupelo.
Lost his wife in a car crash
three years ago.
He's a tourist.
(SIGHS)
Thank you.
Get me Italian Interpol.
(♪♪♪)
(PHONE RINGING)
(IN ITALIAN)
Yes?
Understood.
The operation has been canceled.
Return to headquarters. Quickly.
On the other side.
(IN ITALIAN)
Thanks.
(MAN SPEAKS ITALIAN)
What are you doing?
The I nternet fraud report.
So this is what
Alexander Pearce looks like.
That's above your clearance.
Get back to your work.
(DIALING PHONE)
(SPEAKS RUSSIAN)
(IN ENGLISH) He's fluttering his
eyelids like a girl. That's his tell.
Go all in.
(SPEAKS RUSSIAN)
(CHUCKLES)
(PHONE RINGING)
(IN ENGLISH)
Yes?
I have a piece of information
for Mr. Shaw.
It's concerning Alexander Pearce.
Alexander Pearce just arrived
in Venice
with her.
Hm.
- Valeriy?
- VALERIY: (ON INTERCOM) Sir?
Change of course.
- Venice.
- Yes, sir.
Now, what do I own in Venice?
Frank!
Hi.
- Do you want to come with me?
- What?
Oh, yeah, sure.
I mean, I could use a lift, yeah.
Thank you very...
That's very kind.
Ooh! Oh.
Welcome to Venezia, signora.
The bags.
ELISE: (IN ITALIAN)
Thanks.
Oh, my bags.
(IN ENGLISH)
Are you coming?
Gracias.
(SPEAKING ITALIAN)
(IN ENGLISH)
Elise Clifton-Ward and husband.
(IN ENGLISH) Oh, we arranged
for you a wonderful suite
with, uh,
a bathroom and with...
- May I have your documents?
- Yes.
Thank you.
It would be my pleasure
to show you up personally.
- Please, this way.
- Thank you.
CLERK:
Enjoy your stay, sir.
Thank you.
(SPEAKS ITALIAN)
ALESSIO: Everything was arranged
according to the precise instructions.
I very much hope
you will not be disappointed.
We are entering the Doge's Suite.
It is a room that has been
a home away from home
for Marcel Proust
and Honore de Balzac and others.
- Thank you.
- Oh, thank you.
Have a nice stay, sir.
Thank you.
Make yourself at home.
This really is a very nice hotel,
isn't it?
They think of everything,
don't they?
We know he will be with her. They'll
be staying at one of the grand hotels.
The Gritti, the Regina, the Danieli.
I want you to keep a watch
on all of them.
You can kill the girl,
but you can't kill him.
Not until I have my money, that is.
(IN RUSSIAN)
Understand?
(SPEAKS RUSSIAN)
SHAW:
Let's go.
Fuck.
- You're ravenous.
- Do you mean ravishing?
I do.
You're ravenous.
I am.
Come on.
(♪♪♪)
The scampi and champagne
risotto, please.
Excellent choice. Excellent.
He didn't say that to me.
Did he not like my choice?
Your choice was excellent.
Who is he?
Hotels don't leave gifts like that,
do they?
Who is he?
He's someone who used to be
very important to me.
Used to?
Are you meeting him in Venice?
I hope so.
Part of me hopes I don't.
Why?
Because I don't like being
told what to do.
I don't like being summoned.
But it felt even worse
not hearing from him for two years.
It's the, um, Roman god, Janus.
My mother gave it to me
when I was little.
She wanted it to teach me
that people have two sides.
A good side, a bad side.
A past, a future.
And that we must embrace both
in someone we love.
And I tried.
What's he like?
He's different from anybody I know.
Different's good.
Where I come from
the highest compliment
they can offer a person
is to say
that they're down-to-earth.
Grounded. I hate it.
It drives me nuts.
Would you like another Americano?
I don't know.
Would I?
That really was a very nice
restaurant, wasn't it?
Ooh.
A very nice wine.
I'm making us a nice little drink,
which is very nice of me, isn't it?
Heh, heh, heh.
Thank you.
Were those flowers here
when we checked in?
It's an invitation to a ball
two nights from now.
Ah.
You've been summoned.
It appears I have.
(SIGHS)
May I pay you a compliment?
Another question you need never ask.
You are the least
down-to-earth person
I've ever met.
(CAMERA CLICKING)
It's been a long day.
I do hope the couch
will be comfortable.
Good night.
(DOOR RATTLING)
(♪♪♪)
(CARTRATTLING)
(MAN SPEAKS ITALIAN)
(IN ENGLISH)
Good morning. My name is Guido.
I'm your waiter.
I'm Frank.
What's this?
It's your breakfast, sir.
I didn't order any.
La signora order it for you
when she left.
When she left?
GUIDO:
Have a nice day, sir.
- Hi.
- Alexander. Let's go see an old friend.
What?
(IN RUSSIAN)
He doesn't look like Pearce.
Boss said he might not.
Grab him!
(POUNDING ON DOOR)
(PHONE RINGING)
FRANK:
Hello? Please help.
(SPEAKS ITALIAN)
Bon Jovi. I need help.
There are two men trying
to break down the door.
(IN ENGLISH) I see. What problem
do you have with the door?
No, no. There are two men with guns
trying to break in.
(SPEAKING BROKEN SPANISH)
- Your Spanish is excellent, sir.
- Thank you.
(GUNSHOTS)
- I gotta go!
- Sir?
(GUNSHOTS)
Americans
(IN RUSSIAN) Boss wants
him alive, you idiot!
(IN ITALIAN)
She's coming back.
Frank!
Frank.
(IN ITLALIAN)
Prepare to intervene.
- ACHESON: Yes.
- (IN ENGLISH) Commander Acheson,
two armed men
are chasing the American.
Shots have been fired.
- Request permission to intervene.
- Do you still have Elise?
We still have a visual but
the American is in imminent danger.
ACHESON: The mathematics
teacher from Wisconsin?
I'd say not our mandate.
Sir, this man is in real peril.
This is exactly why she chose him.
To distract us.
Stay with her.
Do not move unless she moves.
Am I making myself crystal clear?
Sir, they will kill him.
Not our mandate.
(♪♪♪)
(MAN SPEAKING RUSSIAN)
Hello? Hello?
Hello?
Oh, God.
(MAN SPEAKING ITALIAN)
(SPEAKS ITALIAN)
COP: (IN ITALIAN)
Headquarters!
Send me backup to the fruit market.
I have a nutcase who wants to jump.
Probably American.
Stop, stop! Please!
Don't do it!
(SCREAMING)
Oh, my God.
I'm so sorry.
Bastard!
Stop him!
(CHUCKLES)
(IN ENGLISH)
I think you need it more than I.
Thank you.
Gracias.
(SPEAKS SPANISH)
You smoke?
(IN ENGLISH)
No, huh?
Now...
you wish to report a murder.
No.
Some people tried to kill me.
I was told
you were reporting a murder.
Attempted murder.
That's not so serious.
No. Not when you downgrade it
from murder.
But when you upgrade it
from room service, it's serious.
So is assaulting a police officer.
- That was an accident.
- The officer feels differently.
With all due respect, sir, I think maybe
I should be talking with someone...
Someone...
not Italian.
Like the embassy or Interpol.
Interpol. Ha, ha.
I'm an American citizen.
- What does that mean?
- I'm involved in something here
and no offense,
this is not a local issue.
What is it
you think you're involved in?
It all started when I met a woman
on the train from Paris.
- This is already good.
- No. No.
She took me to her hotel.
(SPEAKS ITALIAN)
I don't know. No. She's involved
with another man. She's in love.
I'm sorry to hear that.
I know.
Anyway, this man,
whatever his story is,
some people are obviously
trying to kill him.
How do you know this?
Because they tried to kill me.
They tried to kill you?
Yes. Because they must have
thought that I was him.
(SIGHS)
I like you, Mr. Tupelo.
I like you too, sir.
But surely you understand
how strange this all sounds?
Come with me.
Where are you taking me?
- Oh, you're gonna lock me in there?
- Don't worry.
Please don't do this.
Sir, I've done nothing wrong.
- Please.
- It's only until I check some facts.
Hi.
(GRUNTS)
LOMBARDI:
Your facts checked out.
We have to leave.
You're not safe here.
I don't understand.
This has to look right.
Come on.
LOMBARDI: The man you are talking
about is called Alexander Pearce.
He stole big money from a gangster.
They've come to Venice to find him.
They think you are him.
They've placed a...
(LOMBARDI SPEAKS ITALIAN)
A bounty on your head.
That's why you're not safe.
Wait here for a moment.
You've come to buy a key?
Brand-new bills? I appreciate it.
- You think we cheat you?
- Of course not. I just enjoy counting.
Well, gentlemen,
Alexander Pearce is all yours.
(MOTOR REVVING)
MAN: (IN RUSSIAN)
Remember, don't shoot him!
(SPEAKING RUSSIAN)
FRANK:
I think we've lost them.
I'd really like to take these off.
We have to wait to get to open waters.
Okay.
Elise! Elise!
(BOTH SPEAKING RUSSIAN)
(♪♪♪)
(SPEAKS RUSSIAN)
Ah!
Elise!
Argh!
(SPEAKS RUSSIAN)
You all right?
Yeah.
(TAILOR SPEAKING ITALIAN)
(IN ENGLISH)
Do you think it's a little loose?
No, no, no.
(SPEAKS ITALIAN)
(SPEAKING ITALIAN)
(IN RUSSIAN)
They are back.
(IN ENGLISH)
Bring them in.
I come back tomorrow?
No, no. No, stay.
We tried everything, sir.
But he got away.
So I heard. So I heard.
They're referring to the young man
who stole $2.3 billion from me.
Mamma mia.
You know, I worked very hard
for years
so I wouldn't have to do
the dirty work anymore.
No more chasing traitors.
No more killing.
Now I employ people
to do those things for me.
Except that you don't.
(GAGGING & GRUNTING)
- Does it look all right?
- Yes.
Like always.
What's "always"?
Very good.
Yes, I think it looks all right.
Hm, so that's how you pick a lock.
Why do you know how to do that?
Where's the owner of this boat?
Bottom of a canal?
Sitting in a cafe
with a pocketful of euros.
Why is all this happening?
Why is everyone trying to kill me?
It's because I kissed you.
Do I look that much like him?
I am sorry I got you involved
in all this.
Why are you involved in all this?
- Because I'm in love with him.
- Really? I'm not.
Seriously, help me understand why.
I honestly didn't think
he would let it go far.
I didn't think he would let Shaw
get to you.
Shaw. That's the man
that Pearce stole from?
Mm-hm.
Reginald Shaw. Alexander
used to be his private banker.
I thought he'd be Russian
or something like that.
He surrounds himself with Russians,
but he's as English as Alex and I.
Give me your hand.
Now he owns most of the casinos
and brothels from here to Novosibirsk.
Once, he bragged to Alexander
that he had every man killed
his wife had slept with
before she met him.
When he found out how many
there'd been, he killed her too.
There you are.
What made Pearce think
that he could take on a guy like that?
It's just who he is.
Could you ever feel like that
about someone like me?
I don't regret it, you know.
Kissing you.
I have to go check...
the thing.
(MOTOR STARTS)
(♪♪♪)
Where are we going?
FRANK:
The airport.
- Where are we going?
- You'll see.
Tie us off, would you?
I wish we'd met in another life, Frank.
Take the next flight to America.
You'll find what you need in the bag.
Be safe.
(KATIE MELUA'S
"NO FEAR OF HEIGHTS" PLAYING)
But I'm in love with you.
Agent Elise Clifton-Ward,
identification number MFS98495G.
Elise Ward.
Well, you've certainly blown
your cover now.
I'm ready to give you Pearce.
You're ready to give me Pearce.
Well, that's interesting. So you aren't
here to beg me to lift your suspension.
You've actually come to do your job.
Allow me to ask,
Why now?
You live with a man for a year,
during which time we don't get
one single usable photograph.
But now you're ready to give him up.
It's because of that tourist,
isn't it?
I want to put an end to this
before someone gets killed.
Wow.
I wish I could understand
your choice in men.
A fugitive thief.
Well, that's exciting, perhaps.
But a schoolteacher from Wisconsin?
Who'd have thought
your tastes were so provincial?
Do you want Pearce or not?
Yes.
I'm meeting him at a ball tonight.
You know you'll have to wear a wire.
Good.
(♪♪♪)
(CHATTERING)
(SPEAKS ITALIAN)
(ORCHESTRA PLAYING SOFT MUSIC)
AGENT 1: (ON RADIO) She's heading
toward the southeast corner.
MAN:
Where have you been?
I thought you'd never get here.
Really?
MAN: (ON RADIO)
Certainly.
Is that our man?
How could you be so sure
I was coming?
I just knew it.
Fate wouldn't bring me
to an evening like this with no reason.
As soon as you walked in,
I knew what the reason was.
Hm.
No?
No.
AGENT 2: Count Filippo Gaggia. Landowner.
Big reputation as a swordsman.
Well, he won't be dueling tonight.
Wait.
Alexander.
- Excuse me.
- It's Pearce. He's here.
He just left her that envelope.
Pull up the footage, we have his face.
ELISE:
Alexander.
Frank.
I don't bloody believe this.
All right, get that moron out of here.
You shouldn't...
I can't, I'm sorry.
(ORCHESTRA PLAYING WALTZ)
Come on.
You owe me a dance.
You shouldn't be here.
No, Elise, this is the one place
on earth I should be.
How did you get in here?
I told the doorman you were my wife
and I wanted to keep an eye on you.
Italians are big on that kind of thing.
- Leave.
- No.
Do you like the suit?
You paid for it.
I've been thinking about
your friend Pearce and his plan.
And so far, I'm thinking
it hasn't worked out for him.
- No?
- No.
Take that gangster guy.
- Shaw.
- Yeah, Shaw.
I don't believe Pearce was prepared for
him being here for the whole chase.
Will you please leave?
You're kind of worried about me?
Yes.
And I'm worried about you.
Wow.
Frank.
And I'm not leaving without you.
You were part of a plan.
You were useful, that's all.
What do you think, I saw you on
the train and my heart stopped?
Leave.
AGENT 3:
This way, please.
Excuse me, sir,
I think you've made a mista... Ugh!
What's it say?
(♪♪♪)
Bring up Signora Ward's boat,
please.
AGENT 1: It looks like
they've called up her boat.
What should we do?
ACHESON:
She may just be playing with us.
Let's wait.
Fondamenta San Giacomo 23, please.
Okay, good. We have the address.
I'm gonna follow her on the boat.
I want snipers
on all surrounding roofs
and if you get a visual
on Pearce first, call.
(SPEAKS IN DISTINCTLY)
(♪♪♪)
(SPEAKING ITALIAN)
FRANK:
Help.
Hello?
Shh.
(WHISPERING)
Let's have a little fun with him.
(FRANK SPEAKS SPANISH)
Who are you people?
Where are we going?
Well, I don't know, Alexander.
I'm not Alexander.
My name is Frank Tupelo.
I'm an American citizen
and I have rights.
I don't care what you call yourself
these days.
Your name is Alexander Pearce,
and you have no rights.
Not till you pay us 744 million pounds
back taxes.
Seven hundred
and forty-four million?
TOMMASSINI: Looks like someone
else is following our target.
ACHESON:
Reginald Shaw.
Well, this could be fun.
Stay close but not too close, and get
the office to send me an interpreter.
All right.
Yes, 744 million.
You didn't think we knew about
that bank account in Liechtenstein.
I don't know what he's talking about.
Listen...
you asshole.
I know everything about you.
I even know how much that face cost.
Twenty-four million wired to a surgeon
from a Swiss bank account.
I haven't been able to prove it,
but now I don't have to.
Because I just lock you
in a box in a basement
until you tell me where the money is.
Heh, heh, heh. It's all right.
It's all right.
It's all right, Frank.
I know you're not Alexander Pearce.
But you know who you are?
You're a moron.
And you're a moron that almost ruined
my 8-million-pound sting operation.
Twice.
So you're gonna stay here
until this is over.
Please, you can't do this.
I haven't done anything.
I shouldn't be here.
You know what I think?
I think that this is the one place
on earth you really should be.
How was your night in the hotel, huh?
She's quite something, I'm sure.
Target is about 200 yards away
from destination.
We are matching speed.
Good.
But don't get too close.
I don't wanna scare Pearce off again.
(SPEAKS ITALIAN)
(MAN & ELISE SPEAKING ITALIAN)
I won't be needing you anymore
this evening.
Magnificent.
I've never really understood the love
that people devote to each other.
Money, yes. Possessions, yes.
But people are so unreliable.
They sicken, decay and die.
But this... This is worth dying for.
(♪♪♪)
(BLEEPING)
SHAW:
Alexander had taste.
- It seems to me that...
- We're live.
Oh, yes, do sit down.
When are you going in?
You're welcome to stay and watch,
if you can keep your mouth shut.
SHAW: You know,
Alexander was like a son to me.
I loved him.
That brilliant, playful,
disrespectful young bastard.
I even thought he and
I were two of a kind.
Oh, I took great pleasure
never knowing what the scamp
would do next.
Until one day, what he did next
didn't give me any pleasure at all.
You know, in our quaint legal system,
if a man sleeps with my wife,
I kill him and her
and get away scot-free.
Crime of passion is what it's called.
But my passion extends
to all the things I own.
They are me.
They represent me.
So if a man steals from me,
I kill him.
I kill his wife,
his children, his mother.
I might even throw in
the family doctor for good measure.
For he has taken from me something
for which I have paid the infinite price,
My soul.
(CHUCKLES)
(CHUCKLING)
That's something these idiots
will never understand.
He's not coming, is he?
He sent you to get the money.
So...
where is it?
Where's my money?
Where is the safe?
I don't know.
- I don't know.
- You don't know?
Is it behind this bookcase here?
Or...
perhaps this one here.
- Where is the safe?
- I don't know. I haven't seen Alex...
Please, do something.
- Permission to fire.
- Hold your fire.
ACHESON: I repeat, hold your fire.
Not until Pearce shows himself.
You're very beautiful, Elise.
Now, try to combine it
with a little intelligence
and tell me where the safe is.
If I knew it, I would tell you.
(IN RUSSIAN)
I don't think she actually knows.
You have to go in.
They're gonna kill her.
- Where's my interpreter?
- They're going to kill her.
She can handle herself.
She can handle herself?
She's one of us.
Expert in undercover operations.
But when I sent her to Russia
to find Pearce, she went dark.
I think she could never quite decide
if she was with him or with us.
She's a good agent.
Except she invariably falls
in love with any man
that she spends longer
than a train ride with.
Commander Acheson,
I'm the interpreter.
Yes, go.
(SPEAKS ITALIAN)
(SHAW & VIRGINSKY SPEAKING RUSSIAN)
If you could provide me
with some context.
"She really doesn't seem"
"to know where it is.
We should go."
"We give it five more minutes."
"If Pearce doesn't show..."
Pearce.
" If Pearce doesn't show,
we get rid of the woman and go."
SNIPER:
Permission to engage.
- Negative.
- Please.
Not one more word from you.
They won't kill her.
Pearce will come.
He has to come.
All right, let's do it.
(IN RUSSIAN)
No. Knife.
SNIPER:
Engaging target.
Negative. That is an order.
(IN ITALIAN)
This guy is crazy.
Now, if you don't tell me
where the safe is,
I might be tempted
to rearrange your face somewhat.
You'll find life
is not quite so giving
to an ugly woman.
You really don't know, do you?
ELISE:
There.
Behind the medallion. There.
Open it.
There is movement in the courtyard.
ACHESON:
Pearce. I knew it.
You know what?
He does look a little like you.
No!
(♪♪♪)
- I don't...
- Just try.
(BEEPING)
SHAW:
Go on. Press enter.
(BEEPS)
You may try one more time.
(BEEPING)
FRANK:
Let her go.
Oh, my God.
- You let her leave, I'll open the safe.
- Stop right there.
Frank, what in hell?
Please, Elise.
Let me handle this.
I'll say it again.
You let her go, I'll open the safe.
Who the hell are you?
I'm Alexander Pearce.
(IN RUSSIAN)
This was the man on the boat.
- He is not Alexander Pearce.
- FRANK: Elise, please.
- What the hell are you doing?
- ACHESON: What the hell is he doing?
SNIPER:
Permission to engaget arget.
Shut the hell up.
Alexander.
Is it you?
Truly?
Truly.
Show me your teeth.
Alexander had crooked teeth.
Stained from excessive smoking.
Braces. Electronic cigarettes.
He had a higher forehead.
I had a migraine for two weeks
after the remodel.
You sound different.
- Voice-chip implant.
- No, no. I mean, the way you speak.
Yes, that's right.
Alexander was English.
This man is American.
I've gotten used to
the American accent
that I find it a tad difficult
to go back.
That's pathetic.
This man is not Alexander Pearce.
He's a tourist.
A tourist?
Someone I happened to sit
next to on a train.
How would a tourist know you killed
every man your wife ever slept with?
I told him that.
You told a tourist?
Why would she do that?
It's absurd.
Well, there's a simple way
of finding out.
Open the safe.
I've made you a deal.
- When she's gone...
- What are you doing?
And I know she's safe, then...
Well, I'll make you
an even better deal.
Open the safe now, and I won't
make you watch something
that you would never forget.
Open it.
I see.
Now you see.
- Sir.
- I know him. He'll come for her.
I know him.
He won't give her up now.
SNIPER:
We must engage.
Permission to engage, sir.
Sir.
(♪♪♪)
(MOUTH ING)
I love you.
He'll come for her. He'll come for her.
It doesn't make se...
This is Chief Inspector Jones.
Permission granted.
Fire.
(FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING)
(GUNSHOT)
- Are you all right?
- Yes.
Agent Ward,
your suspension's lifted.
Thank you, sir.
And your employment is terminated.
Effective immediately.
Thank you, sir.
AGENT: (ON RADIO)
We got him.
- We got Alexander Pearce.
- Where?
On the Fondamenta.
Three hundred meters
south of your location.
(AGENTS SPEAKING ITALIAN)
(BOATS PEEDING AWAY)
So you love me.
I do.
How do you feel about
Alexander Pearce these days?
I love him too. Unfortunately.
I may have a solution for you.
(BEEPING)
(♪♪♪)
Are you with me this time?
JONES:
Come on. Let him up.
I'm just a tourist.
He said I might get
arrested at some point.
- What?
- But that you'd have to let me go
because you'd have nothing on me.
- Who?
- The man that's sending me texts.
- Texts?
- And the money, of course.
So let me get this straight
because I'm a little confused.
You receive money
from a man you've never met before
who sends you text messages
telling you just to show up somewhere.
Well...
not just anywhere.
(BEEPING)
Clear.
(♪♪♪)
"Seven hundred and forty-four million."
Inspector Acheson,
this operation
is now officially terminated.
- I'll expect your report on Monday.
- Sir, listen.
- We have our money, Acheson.
- But we don't have Pearce.
The man's a criminal
wanted in 14 countries.
Well, what is it he did, really?
He stole money from a gangster.
A dead gangster.
And he has good taste in women.
I can't say I don't wish him well.
(♪♪♪)
Twenty million dollars'
worth of plastic surgery.
And that's the face you choose?
Do you not like it?
It'll do.